<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Daphnaïda An elegie vpon the death of the noble and vertuous Douglas Howard, daughter and heire of Henry Lord Howard, Viscount Byndon, and wife of Arthure Gorges Esquier. Dedicated to the Right honorable the Lady Helena, Marquesse of Northampton. By Ed. Sp.</title>
            <author>Spenser, Edmund, 1552?-1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111271</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846646</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846646</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11630</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11630)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 354:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Daphnaïda An elegie vpon the death of the noble and vertuous Douglas Howard, daughter and heire of Henry Lord Howard, Viscount Byndon, and wife of Arthure Gorges Esquier. Dedicated to the Right honorable the Lady Helena, Marquesse of Northampton. By Ed. Sp.</title>
                  <author>Spenser, Edmund, 1552?-1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Orwin] for VVilliam Ponsonby, dwelling in Paules Churchyard at the signe of the Bishops head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ed. Sp. = Edmund Spenser.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>[Gorges, Douglas (Howard), --  Lady, d. 1590] --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11630:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Daphnaïda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Elegie vpon the death of the noble and vertuous Douglas Howard, <hi>Daughter and</hi> heire of <hi>Henry</hi> Lord <hi>Howard, Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Byndon, and wife of</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thure Gorges <hi>Eſquier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dedicated to the Right honorable the Lady Helena,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Northampton.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Ed. Sp.</p>
            <p>AT LONDON <hi>Printed for</hi> William Ponſonby, <hi>dwelling in</hi> Paules Churchyard at the ſigne of the Biſhops head 1591.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11630:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11630:2"/>
            <head>To the right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and vertuous Lady <hi>Helena Marqueſse of</hi> North-hampton.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue the rather preſumed</hi> humbly to offer vnto your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor the dedication of this little Poëme, for that the noble and vertuous Gentlewoman of whom it is written, was by match neere alied, and in affection greatly deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto your Ladiſhip. The occaſion why J wrote the ſame, was aſwell the great good fame which J heard of her deceaſſed, as the particular good will which J beare vnto her huſband Maſter <hi>Arthure Gorges,</hi> a louer of learning and vertue, whoſe houſe as your Ladiſhip by mariage hath honoured, ſo doo J finde the name of them by many notable records, to be of great antiquitie in this Realm; and ſuch as haue euer borne themſelues with honorable
<pb facs="tcp:11630:3"/>reputation to the world, and vnſpotted loyaltie to their Prince and Countrey: beſides ſo linially are they deſcended from the <hi>Howards,</hi> as that the Lady <hi>Anne Howard,</hi> eldeſt daughter to <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Norfolke,</hi> was wife to Sir <hi>Edmund,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Sir <hi>Edward,</hi> and grandmother to Sir <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> and Sir <hi>Thomas Gorges</hi> Knights. And therefore J doo aſſure my ſelfe that no due honour done to the white Lyon, but will be moſt gratefull to your Ladiſhip, whoſe huſband and children doe ſo neerely participate with the bloud of that noble familie. So in all duetie J recommend this Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, &amp; the good acceptance thereof to your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable fauour and protection. <hi>London</hi> this firſt of January. 1591.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors humbly euer. <hi>E. Sp.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:11630:3"/>
            <head>Daphnaïda.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat euer man he be, whoſe heauie minde</l>
               <l>With griefe of mournefull great miſhap oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Fit matter for his cares increaſe would finde:</l>
               <l>Let reade the rufull plaint herein expreſt</l>
               <l>Of one (I weene) the wofulſt man aliue;</l>
               <l>Euen ſad <hi>Aleyon,</hi> whoſe empierced breſt</l>
               <l>Sharpe ſorrowe did in thouſand peeces riue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But who ſo elſe in pleaſure findeth ſenſe,</l>
               <l>Or in this wretched life dooth take delight,</l>
               <l>Let him be baniſht farre away from hence:</l>
               <l>Ne let the ſacred Siſters here be hight,</l>
               <l>Though they of ſorrowe heauilie can ſing;</l>
               <l>For euen their heauie ſong would breede delight:</l>
               <l>But here no tunes, ſaue ſobs and grones ſhall ring.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In ſtead of them, and their ſweete harmonie,</l>
               <l>Let thoſe three fatall Siſters, whoſe ſad hands</l>
               <l>Doo weaue the direfull threds of deſtinie,</l>
               <l>And in their wrath breake off the vitall bands,</l>
               <l>Approach hereto: and let the dreadfull Queene</l>
               <l>Of darkenes deepe come from the Stygian ſtrands,</l>
               <l>And griſly Ghoſts to heare this dolefull teene.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:4"/>
               <l>In gloomie euening, when the wearie Sun</l>
               <l>After his dayes long labour drew to reſt,</l>
               <l>And ſweatie ſteeds now hauing ouer run</l>
               <l>The compaſt ſkie, gan water in the weſt,</l>
               <l>I walkt abroade to breath the freſhing ayre</l>
               <l>In open fields, whoſe flowring pride oppreſt</l>
               <l>With early froſts, had loſt their beautie faire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There came vnto my minde a troublous thought,</l>
               <l>Which dayly dooth my weaker wit poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>Ne lets it reſt, vntill it forth haue brought</l>
               <l>Her long borne Infant, fruit of heauineſſe,</l>
               <l>Which ſhe conceiued hath through meditation</l>
               <l>Of this worlds vainneſſe and lifes wretchedneſſe,</l>
               <l>That yet my ſoule it deepely doth empaſſion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So as I muzed on the miſerie,</l>
               <l>In which men liue, and I of many moſt,</l>
               <l>Moſt miſerable man; I did eſpie</l>
               <l>Where towards me a ſory wight did coſt,</l>
               <l>Clad all in black, that mourning did bewray:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iaakob</hi> ſtaffe in hand deuoutlie croſt,</l>
               <l>Like to ſome Pilgrim come from farre away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His careleſſe locks, vncombed and vnſhorne</l>
               <l>Hong long adowne, and beard all ouer growne,</l>
               <l>That well he ſeemd to be ſum wight forlorne;</l>
               <l>Downe to the earth his heauie eyes were throwne</l>
               <l>As loathing light: and euer as he went,</l>
               <l>He ſighed ſoft, and inly deepe did grone,</l>
               <l>As if his heart in peeces would haue rent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:4"/>
               <l>Approaching nigh, his face I vewed nere,</l>
               <l>And by the ſemblant of his countenance,</l>
               <l>Me ſeemd I had his perſon ſeene elſewhere,</l>
               <l>Moſt like <hi>Alcyon</hi> ſeeming at a glaunce;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aleyon</hi> he, the iollie Shepheard ſwaine,</l>
               <l>That wont full merrilie to pipe and daunce,</l>
               <l>And fill with pleaſance euery wood and plaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet halfe in doubt becauſe of his diſguize,</l>
               <l>I ſoſtlie ſayd <hi>Alcyon?</hi> There with all</l>
               <l>He lookt a ſide as in diſdainefull wiſe,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtayed not: till I againe did call.</l>
               <l>Then turning back he ſaide with hollow ſound,</l>
               <l>Who is it, that dooth name me, wofull thrall,</l>
               <l>The wretchedſt man that treades this day on ground?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>One, whome like wofulneſſe impreſſed deepe</l>
               <l>Hath made fit mate thy wretched caſe to heare,</l>
               <l>And giuen like cauſe with thee to waile and weepe:</l>
               <l>Griefe findes ſome eaſe by him that like does beare,</l>
               <l>Then ſtay <hi>Alcyon,</hi> gentle ſhepheard ſtay,</l>
               <l>(Quoth I) till thou haue to my truſtie eare</l>
               <l>Committed, what thee dooth ſo ill apay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ceaſe fooliſh man (ſaide he halfe wrothfully)</l>
               <l>To ſeeke to heare that which cannot be tolde.</l>
               <l>For the huge anguiſh, which dooth multiplie</l>
               <l>My dying paines, no tongue can well vnfold:</l>
               <l>Ne doo I care, that any ſhould bemone</l>
               <l>My hard miſhap, or any weepe that would,</l>
               <l>But ſeeke alone to weepe, and dye alone.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:5"/>
               <l>Then be it ſo (quoth I) that thou art bent</l>
               <l>To die alone, vnpiried, vnplained,</l>
               <l>Yet ere thou die, it were conuenient</l>
               <l>To tell the cauſe, which thee theretoo conſtrained:</l>
               <l>Leaſt that the world thee dead accuſe of guilt,</l>
               <l>And ſay, when thou of none ſhalt be maintained,</l>
               <l>That thou for ſecret crime thy blood haſt ſpilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Who life dooes loath, and longs to bee vnbound</l>
               <l>From the ſtrong ſhackles of fraile fleſh (quoth he)</l>
               <l>Nought cares at all, what they that liue on ground</l>
               <l>Deeme the occaſion of his death to bee:</l>
               <l>Rather deſires to be forgotten quight,</l>
               <l>Than queſtion made of his calamitie,</l>
               <l>For harts deep ſorrow hates both life and light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſince ſo much thou ſeemſt to rue my griefe,</l>
               <l>And careſt for one that for himſelfe cares nought,</l>
               <l>(Signe of thy loue, though nought for my reliefe:</l>
               <l>For my reliefe exceedeth liuing thought)</l>
               <l>I will to thee this heauie caſe relate,</l>
               <l>Then harken well till it to ende bee brought,</l>
               <l>For neuer didſt thou heare more hapleſſe fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whilome I vſde (as thou right well doeſt know)</l>
               <l>My little flocke on weſterne downes to keepe.</l>
               <l>Not far from whence <hi>Sabrinaes</hi> ſtreame doth flow,</l>
               <l>And flowrie bancks with ſiluer liquor ſteepe:</l>
               <l>Nought carde I then for worldly change or chaunce,</l>
               <l>For all my ioy was on my gentle ſheepe,</l>
               <l>And to my pype to caroll and to daunce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:5"/>
               <l>It there befell as I the fields did range</l>
               <l>Feareleſſe and free, a faire young Lioneſſe,</l>
               <l>White as the natiue Roſe before the chaunge,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Venus</hi> blood did in her leaues impreſſe,</l>
               <l>I ſpied playing on the graſſie playne</l>
               <l>Her youthfull ſports and kindlie wantonneſſe.</l>
               <l>That did all other Beaſts in beawtie ſtaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Much was I moued at ſo goodly ſight;</l>
               <l>Whoſe like before mine eye had ſeldome ſeene,</l>
               <l>And gan to caſt, how I her compaſſe might,</l>
               <l>And bring to hand, that yet had neuer beene:</l>
               <l>So well I wrought with mildnes and with paine,</l>
               <l>That I her caught diſporting on the grene,</l>
               <l>And brought away faſt bound with ſiluer chaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And afterwards I handled her ſo fayre,</l>
               <l>That though by kind ſhee ſtout and ſaluage were,</l>
               <l>For being borne an auncient Lions haire,</l>
               <l>And of the race, that all wild beaſtes do feare;</l>
               <l>Yet I her fram'd and wan ſo to my bent,</l>
               <l>That ſhee became ſo meeke and milde of cheare,</l>
               <l>As the leaſt lamb in all my flock that went.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For ſhee in field, where euer I did wend,</l>
               <l>Would wend with me, and waite by me all day:</l>
               <l>And all the night that I in watch did ſpend,</l>
               <l>If cauſe requir'd, or els in ſleepe, if nay,</l>
               <l>Shee would all night by mee or watch, or ſleepe;</l>
               <l>And euermore when I did ſleepe or play,</l>
               <l>She of my flock would take full warie keepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Safe then and ſafeſt were my ſillie ſheepe,</l>
               <l>Ne fear'd the Wolfe, ne fear'd the wildeſt beaſt:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:6"/>
               <l>All were I drown'd in careleſſe quiet deepe:</l>
               <l>My louelie Lioneſſe without beheaſt</l>
               <l>So carefull was for them and for my good,</l>
               <l>That when I waked, neither moſt nor leaſt</l>
               <l>I found miſcaried or in plaine or wood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oft did the Shepeheards, which my hap did heare,</l>
               <l>And oft their laſſes which my luck enuide,</l>
               <l>Daylie reſort to me from farre and neare,</l>
               <l>To ſee my Lyoneſſe, whoſe praiſes wide</l>
               <l>Were ſpred abroad; and when her worthineſſe</l>
               <l>Much greater than the rude report they tri'de,</l>
               <l>They her did praiſe, and my good fortune bleſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Long thus I ioyed in my happineſſe,</l>
               <l>And well did hope my ioy would haue no end:</l>
               <l>But oh fond man, that in worlds fickleneſſe</l>
               <l>Repoſedſt hope, or weenedſt her thy frend,</l>
               <l>That glories moſt in mortall miſeries,</l>
               <l>And daylie doth her changefull counſels bend:</l>
               <l>To make new matter fit for Tragedies.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For whileſt I was thus without dread or dout,</l>
               <l>A cruell <hi>Satyre</hi> with his murdrous dart,</l>
               <l>Greedie of miſchiefe ranging all about,</l>
               <l>Gaue her the fatall wound of deadlie ſmart:</l>
               <l>And reft fro me my ſweete companion,</l>
               <l>And reft fro me my loue, my life, my hart,</l>
               <l>My Lyoneſſe (ah woe is mee) is gon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Out of the world thus was ſhe reft awaie,</l>
               <l>Out of the world, vnworthie ſuch a ſpoyle;</l>
               <l>And borne to heauen, for heauen a fitter pray:</l>
               <l>Much fitter than the Lyon, which with toyle</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:6"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcides</hi> ſlew, and fixt in firmament;</l>
               <l>Her now I ſeek throughout this earthlie ſoyle,</l>
               <l>And ſeeking miſſe, and miſsing doe lament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therewith he gan afreſh to waile and weepe,</l>
               <l>That I for pittie of his heauie plight.</l>
               <l>Could not abſtaine mine eyes with teares to ſteepe:</l>
               <l>But when I ſaw the anguiſh of his ſpright</l>
               <l>Some deale alaid, I him beſpake againe.</l>
               <l>Certes <hi>Alcyon,</hi> painfull is thy plight,</l>
               <l>That it in me breeds almoſt equall paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet doth not my dull wit well vnderſtand</l>
               <l>The riddle of thy loued Lioneſſe;</l>
               <l>For rare it ſeemes in reaſon to be ſkand</l>
               <l>That man, who doth the whole worlds rule poſſeſſe</l>
               <l>Should to a beaſt his noble hart embaſe,</l>
               <l>And be the vaſſall of his vaſſaleſſe:</l>
               <l>Therefore more plaine aread this doubtfull caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſighing ſore, <hi>Daphne</hi> thou kneweſt (quoth he)</l>
               <l>She now is dead; ne more endured to ſay:</l>
               <l>But fell to ground for great extreamitie,</l>
               <l>That I beholding it, with deepe diſmay</l>
               <l>Was much appald, and lightlie him vprearing,</l>
               <l>Reuoked life that would haue fled away,</l>
               <l>All were my ſelf through griefe in deadly drearing.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then gan I him to comfort all my beſt,</l>
               <l>And with milde counſaile ſtroue to mitigate</l>
               <l>The ſtormie paſsion of his troubled breſt,</l>
               <l>But he thereby was more empaſsionate:</l>
               <l>As ſtubborne ſteed, that is with curb reſtrained,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:7"/>
               <l>Becomes more fierce and ferue nt in his gate;</l>
               <l>And breaking foorth at laſt, thus dearnelie plained.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>1 What man henceforth, that breatheth vitall ayre,</l>
               <l>Will honour heauen, or heauenlie powers adore?</l>
               <l>Which ſo vniuſtlie doe their iudgments ſhare;</l>
               <l>Mongſt earthlie wightes, as to afflict ſo ſore</l>
               <l>The innocent, as thoſe which do tranſgreſſe,</l>
               <l>And do not ſpare the beſt or fayreſt more,</l>
               <l>Than worſt or fowleſt, but doe both oppreſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If this be right, why did they then create</l>
               <l>The world ſo fayre, ſith faireneſſe is neglected?</l>
               <l>Or whie be they themſelues immaculate,</l>
               <l>If pureſt things be not by them reſpected?</l>
               <l>She faire, ſhee pure, moſt faire moſt pure ſhee was,</l>
               <l>Yet was by them as thing impure reiected:</l>
               <l>Yet ſhee in pureneſſe, heauen it ſelfe did pas.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In pureneſſe and in all celeſtiall grace,</l>
               <l>That men admire in goodlie womankinde,</l>
               <l>Shee did excell and ſeem'd of Angels race</l>
               <l>Liuing on earth like Angell new diuinde,</l>
               <l>Adorn'd with wiſedome and with chaſtitie:</l>
               <l>And all the dowries of a noble mind,</l>
               <l>Which did her beautie much more beautifie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No age hath bred (ſince fayre <hi>Aſtraea</hi> left</l>
               <l>The ſinfull world) more vertue in a wight,</l>
               <l>And when ſhe parted hence, with her ſhe reft</l>
               <l>Great hope; and robd her race of bountie quight:</l>
               <l>Well may the ſhepheard laſſes now lament,</l>
               <l>For dubble loſſe by her hath on them light;</l>
               <l>To looſe both her and bounties ornament.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:7"/>
               <l>Ne let <hi>Eliſa</hi> royall Shepheardeſſe</l>
               <l>The praiſes of my parted loue enuy,</l>
               <l>For ſhe hath praiſes in all plenteouſneſſe</l>
               <l>Powr'd vpon her like ſhowers of <hi>Caſtaly</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By her own Shepheard, <hi>Colin</hi> her owne Shepherd,</l>
               <l>That her with heauenly hymnes doth deifie,</l>
               <l>Of ruſtick muſe full hardly to be betterd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She is the Roſe, the glorie of the day,</l>
               <l>And mine the Primroſe in the lowly ſhade,</l>
               <l>Mine, ah not mine; amiſſe I mine did ſay:</l>
               <l>Not mine but his, which mine awhile her made:</l>
               <l>Mine to be his, with him to liue for ay:</l>
               <l>O that ſo faire a flower ſo ſoone ſhould fade,</l>
               <l>And through vntimely tempeſt fall away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>She fell away in her firſt ages ſpring,</l>
               <l>Whil'ſt yet her leafe was greene, &amp; freſh her rinde,</l>
               <l>And whil'ſt her braunch faire bloſſomes foorth did bring,</l>
               <l>She fell away againſt all courſe of kinde:</l>
               <l>For age to dye is right, but youth is wrong;</l>
               <l>She fel away like fruit blowne downe with winde:</l>
               <l>Weepe Shepheard weepe to make my vnderſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>2 What hart ſo ſtony hard, but that would weepe,</l>
               <l>And poure foorth fountaines of inceſſant teares?</l>
               <l>What <hi>Timon,</hi> but would let compaſsion creepe</l>
               <l>Into his breſt, and pierce his froſen eares?</l>
               <l>In ſtead of teares, whoſe brackiſh bitter well</l>
               <l>I waſted haue, my heart blood dropping weares,</l>
               <l>To thinke to ground how that faire bloſſome fell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet fell ſhe not, as one enforſt to dye,</l>
               <l>Ne dyde with dread and grudging diſcontent</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:8"/>
               <l>But as one toyld with trauaile downe doth lye,</l>
               <l>So lay ſhe downe, as if to ſleepe ſhe went,</l>
               <l>And cloſde her eyes with careleſſe quietneſſe;</l>
               <l>The whiles ſoft death away her ſpirit hent,</l>
               <l>And ſoule aſſoyld from ſinfull fleſhlineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ere that life her lodging did forſake,</l>
               <l>She all reſolu'd and ready to remoue,</l>
               <l>Calling to me (ay me) this wiſe beſpake;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alcyon,</hi> ah my firſt and lateſt loue,</l>
               <l>Ah why does my <hi>Alcyon</hi> weepe and mourne,</l>
               <l>And grieue my ghoſt, that ill mote him behoue,</l>
               <l>As if to me had chanſt ſome euill tourne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I, ſince the meſſenger is come for mee,</l>
               <l>That ſummons ſoules vnto the bridale feaſt</l>
               <l>Of his great Lord, muſt needes depart from thee,</l>
               <l>And ſtraight obay his ſoueraine beheaſt:</l>
               <l>Why ſhould <hi>Alcyon</hi> then ſo ſore lament,</l>
               <l>That I from miſerie ſhall be releaſt,</l>
               <l>And freed from wretched long impriſonment?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our daies are full of dolor and diſeaſe,</l>
               <l>Our life afflicted with inceſſant paine,</l>
               <l>That nought on earth may leſſen or appeaſe.</l>
               <l>Why then ſhould I deſire here to remaine?</l>
               <l>Or why ſhould he that loues me, ſorie bee</l>
               <l>For my deliuerance, or at all complaine</l>
               <l>My good to heare, and toward ioyes to ſee?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I goe, and long deſired haue to goe,</l>
               <l>I goe with gladneſſe to my wiſhed reſt,</l>
               <l>Whereas no worlds ſad care, nor waſting woe</l>
               <l>May come their happie quiet to moleſt,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:8"/>
               <l>But Saints and Angels in celeſtiall thrones</l>
               <l>Eternally him praiſe, that hath them bleſt,</l>
               <l>There ſhall I be amongſt thoſe bleſſed ones.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ere I goe, a pledge I leaue with thee</l>
               <l>Of the late loue, the which betwixt vs paſt,</l>
               <l>My yong <hi>Ambroſia,</hi> in lieu of mee</l>
               <l>Loue her: ſo ſhall our loue for euer laſt.</l>
               <l>Thus deare adieu, whom I expect ere long:</l>
               <l>So hauing ſaid, away ſhe ſoftly paſt:</l>
               <l>Weep Shepheard weep, to make mine vnderſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>3 So oft as I record thoſe piercing words,</l>
               <l>Which yet are deepe engrauen in my breſt,</l>
               <l>And thoſe laſt deadly accents, which like ſwords</l>
               <l>Did wound my heart and rend my bleeding cheſt,</l>
               <l>With thoſe ſweet ſugred ſpeaches doo compare,</l>
               <l>The which my ſoule firſt conquerd and poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>The firſt beginners of my endles care;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when thoſe pallid cheekes and aſhy hew,</l>
               <l>In which ſad death his pourtraicture had writ,</l>
               <l>And when thoſe hollow eyes and deadly view,</l>
               <l>On which the clowde of ghaſtly night did ſit,</l>
               <l>I match with that ſweet ſmile and chearfull brow,</l>
               <l>Which all the world ſubdued vnto it;</l>
               <l>How happie was I then, and wretched now?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>How happie was I, when I ſaw her leade</l>
               <l>The Shepheards daughters dauncing in a rownd?</l>
               <l>How trimly would ſhe trace and ſoftly tread</l>
               <l>The tender graſſe with roſie garland crownd?</l>
               <l>And when ſhe liſt aduance her heauenly voyce,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:9"/>
               <l>Both Nimphs and Muſes nigh ſhe made aſtownd,</l>
               <l>And flocks and ſhepheards cauſed to reioyce.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now ye Shepheard laſſes, who ſhall lead</l>
               <l>Your wandring troupes, or ſing your virelayes?</l>
               <l>Or who ſhall dight your bowres, ſith ſhe is dead</l>
               <l>That was the Lady of your holy dayes?</l>
               <l>Let now your bliſſe be turned into bale,</l>
               <l>And into plaints conuert your ioyous playes,</l>
               <l>And with the ſame fill euery hill and dale.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let Bagpipe neuer more be heard to ſhrill,</l>
               <l>That may allure the ſenſes to delight;</l>
               <l>Ne euer Shepheard ſound his Oaten quill</l>
               <l>Vnto the many, that prouoke them might</l>
               <l>To idle pleaſance: but let ghaſtlineſſe</l>
               <l>And drery horror dim the chearfull light,</l>
               <l>To make the image of true heauineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let birds be ſilent on the naked ſpray,</l>
               <l>And ſhady woods reſound with dreadfull yells:</l>
               <l>Let ſtreaming floods their haſtie courſes ſtay,</l>
               <l>And parching drougth drie vp the chriſtall wells;</l>
               <l>Let th'earth be barren and bring foorth no flowres,</l>
               <l>And th'ayre be fild with noyſe of dolefull knells,</l>
               <l>And wandring ſpirits walke vntimely howres.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And Nature nurſe of euery liuing thing,</l>
               <l>Let reſt her ſelfe from her long wearineſſe,</l>
               <l>And ceaſe henceforth things kindly forth to bring,</l>
               <l>But hideous monſters full of vglineſſe:</l>
               <l>For ſhe it is, that hath me done this wrong,</l>
               <l>No nurſe, but Stepdame cruell mercileſſe,</l>
               <l>Weepe Shepheard weepe to make my vnder ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:9"/>
               <l>4 My little flocke, whom earſt I lou'd ſo well,</l>
               <l>And wont to feede with fineſt graſſe that grew,</l>
               <l>Feede ye hencefoorth on bitter <hi>Astrofell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſtinking Smallage, and vnſauerie Rew;</l>
               <l>And when your mawes are with thoſe weeds corrupted,</l>
               <l>Be ye the pray of Wolues: ne will I rew,</l>
               <l>That with your carkaſſes wild beaſts be glutted.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ne worſe to you my ſillie ſheepe I pray,</l>
               <l>Ne ſorer vengeance wiſh on you to fall</l>
               <l>Than to my ſelfe, for whoſe confuſde decay</l>
               <l>To careleſſe heauens I doo daylie call:</l>
               <l>But heauens refuſe to heare a wretches cry,</l>
               <l>And cruell death doth ſcorne to come at call,</l>
               <l>Or graunt his boone that moſt deſires to dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The good and righteous he away doth take,</l>
               <l>To plagueth vnrighteous which aliue remaine:</l>
               <l>But the vngodly ones he doth forſake,</l>
               <l>By liuing long to multiplie their paine:</l>
               <l>Els ſurely death ſhould be no puniſhment,</l>
               <l>As the great Iudge at firſt did it ordaine,</l>
               <l>But rather riddance from long languiſhment.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Therefore my <hi>Daphne</hi> they haue tane away;</l>
               <l>For worthie of a better place was ſhe:</l>
               <l>But me vnworthie willed here to ſtay,</l>
               <l>That with her lacke I might tormented be.</l>
               <l>Sith then they ſo haue ordred, I will pay</l>
               <l>Penance to her according their decree,</l>
               <l>And to her ghoſt doo ſeruice day by day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For I will walke this wandring pilgrimage</l>
               <l>Throughout the world from one to other end,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:10"/>
               <l>And in affliction waſt my better age.</l>
               <l>My bread ſhall be the anguiſh of my mind,</l>
               <l>My drink the teares which fro mine eyes do raine,</l>
               <l>My bed the ground that hardeſt I may finde;</l>
               <l>So will I wilfully increaſe my paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ſhe my loue that was, my Saint that is,</l>
               <l>When ſhe beholds from her celeſtiall throne,</l>
               <l>(In which ſhee ioyeth in eternall blis)</l>
               <l>My bitter penance, will my caſe bemone,</l>
               <l>And pitie me that liuing thus doo die:</l>
               <l>For heauenly ſpirits haue compaſsion</l>
               <l>On mortall men, and rue their miſerie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So when I haue with ſorowe ſatiſfide</l>
               <l>Th'importune fates, which vengeance on me ſeeke,</l>
               <l>And th'eauens with long languor pacifide,</l>
               <l>She for pure pitie of my ſufferance meeke,</l>
               <l>Will ſend for me; for which I daylie long,</l>
               <l>And will tell then my painfull penance eeke:</l>
               <l>Weep Shepheard, weep to make my vnder ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>5 Hencefoorth I hate what euer Nature made,</l>
               <l>And in her workmanſhip no pleaſure finde:</l>
               <l>For they be all but vaine, and quickly fade,</l>
               <l>So ſoone as on them blowes the Northern winde,</l>
               <l>They tarrie not, but flit and fall away,</l>
               <l>Leauing behind them nought but griefe of minde,</l>
               <l>And mocking ſuch as thinke they long will ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I hate the heauen, becauſe it doth withhold</l>
               <l>Me from my loue, and eke my loue from me;</l>
               <l>I hate the earth, becauſe it is the mold</l>
               <l>Of fleſhly ſlime and fraile mortalitie;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:10"/>
               <l>I hate the fire, becauſe to nought it flyes,</l>
               <l>I hate the Ayre, becauſe ſighes of it be,</l>
               <l>I hate the Sea, becauſe it teares ſupplyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I hate the day, becauſe it lendeth light</l>
               <l>To ſee all things, and not my loue to ſee;</l>
               <l>I hate the darkneſſe and the drery night,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they breed ſad balefulneſſe in mee:</l>
               <l>I hate all times, becauſe all times doo flye</l>
               <l>So faſt away, and may not ſtayed bee,</l>
               <l>But as a ſpeedie poſt that paſſeth by.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I hate to ſpeake, my voyce is ſpent with crying:</l>
               <l>I hate to heare, lowd plaints haue duld mine eares:</l>
               <l>I hate to taſt, for food withholds my dying:</l>
               <l>I hate to ſee, mine eyes are dimd with teares:</l>
               <l>I hate to ſmell, no ſweet on earth is left:</l>
               <l>I hate to feele, my fleſh is numbd with feares:</l>
               <l>So all my ſenſes from me are bereft.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I hate all men, and ſhun all womankinde;</l>
               <l>The one becauſe as I they wretched are,</l>
               <l>The other for becauſe I doo not finde</l>
               <l>My loue with them, that wont to be their Starre:</l>
               <l>And life I hate, becauſe it will not laſt,</l>
               <l>And death I hate, becauſe it life doth marre,</l>
               <l>And all I hate, that is to come or paſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So all the world, and all in it I hate,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it changeth euer too and fro,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſtandeth in one certaine ſtate,</l>
               <l>But ſtill vnſtedfaſt round about doth goe,</l>
               <l>Like a Mill wheele, in midſt of miſerie,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:11"/>
               <l>Driuen with ſtreames of wretchedneſſe and woe,</l>
               <l>That dying liues, and liuing ſtill does dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So doo I liue, ſo doo I daylie die,</l>
               <l>And pine away in ſelfe-confuming paine,</l>
               <l>Sith ſhe that did my vitall powres ſupplie,</l>
               <l>And feeble ſpirits in their force maintaine</l>
               <l>Is fetcht fro me, why ſeeke I to prolong</l>
               <l>My wearie daies in dolor and diſdaine?</l>
               <l>Weep Shepheard weep to make my vnder ſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>6 Why doo I longer liue in lifes deſpight?</l>
               <l>And doo not dye then in deſpight of death:</l>
               <l>Why doo I longer ſee this loathſome light,</l>
               <l>And doo in darkneſſe not abridge my breath,</l>
               <l>Sith all my ſorrow ſhould haue end thereby,</l>
               <l>And cares finde quiet; is it ſo vneath</l>
               <l>To leaue this life, or dolorous to dye?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>To liue I finde it deadly dolorous;</l>
               <l>For life drawes care, and care continuall woe:</l>
               <l>Therefore to dye muſt needes be ioyeous,</l>
               <l>And wiſhfull thing this ſad life to forgoe.</l>
               <l>But I muſt ſtay; I may it not amend,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Daphne</hi> hence departing bad me ſo,</l>
               <l>She bad me ſtay, till ſhe for me did ſend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet whileſt I in this wretched vale doo ſtay,</l>
               <l>My wearie feete ſhall euer wandring be,</l>
               <l>That ſtill I may be readie on my way,</l>
               <l>When as her meſſenger doth come for me:</l>
               <l>Ne will I reſt my feete for feebleneſſe,</l>
               <l>Ne will I reſt my limmes for frailtie,</l>
               <l>Ne will I reſt mine eyes for heauineſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:11"/>
               <l>But as the mother of the Gods, that ſought</l>
               <l>For faire <hi>Eurydice</hi> her daughter deere</l>
               <l>Throghout the world, with wofull heauie thought;</l>
               <l>So will I trauell whileſt I tarrie heere,</l>
               <l>Ne will I lodge, ne will I euer lin,</l>
               <l>Ne when as drouping <hi>Titan</hi> draweth neere</l>
               <l>To looſe his teeme, will I take vp my Innne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ne ſleepe (the harbenger of wearie wights)</l>
               <l>Shall euer lodge vpon mine ey-lids more;</l>
               <l>Ne ſhall with reſt refreſh my fainting ſprights,</l>
               <l>Nor failing force to former ſtrength reſtore,</l>
               <l>But I will wake and ſorrow all the night</l>
               <l>With <hi>Philumene,</hi> my fortune to deplore,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Philumene,</hi> the partner of my plight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And euer as I ſee the ſtarres to fall,</l>
               <l>And vnder ground to goe, to giue them light</l>
               <l>Which dwell in darknes, I to minde will call,</l>
               <l>How my faire Starre (that ſhinde on me ſo bright)</l>
               <l>Fell ſodainly, and faded vnder ground;</l>
               <l>Since whoſe departure, day is turned to night,</l>
               <l>And night without a <hi>Venus</hi> ſtarre is found.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſoone as day doth ſhew his deawie face,</l>
               <l>And calls foorth men vnto their toylſome trade,</l>
               <l>I will withdraw me to ſome darkſome place,</l>
               <l>Or ſome deepe caue, or ſolitarie ſhade;</l>
               <l>There will I ſigh and ſorrow all day long,</l>
               <l>And the huge burden of my cares vnlade:</l>
               <l>Weep Shepheard, weep, to make my vnderſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>7 Hence foorth mine eyes ſhall neuer more behold</l>
               <l>Faire thing on earth, ne feed on falſe delight</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:12"/>
               <l>Of ought that framed is of mortall moulde,</l>
               <l>Sith that my faireſt flower is faded quight:</l>
               <l>For all I ſee is vaine and tranſitorie,</l>
               <l>Ne will be helde in anie ſtedfaſt plight,</l>
               <l>But in a moment looſe their grace and glorie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye fond men on fortunes wheele that ride,</l>
               <l>Or in ought vnder heauen repoſe aſſurance,</l>
               <l>Be it riches, beautie, or honors pride:</l>
               <l>Be ſure that they ſhall haue no long endurance,</l>
               <l>But ere ye be aware will flit away;</l>
               <l>For nought of them is yours, but th'onely vſance</l>
               <l>Of a ſmall time, which none aſcertaine may.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye true Louers, whom deſaſtrous chaunce</l>
               <l>Hath farre exiled from your Ladies grace,</l>
               <l>To mourne in ſorrow and ſad ſufferaunce,</l>
               <l>When ye doo heare me in that deſert place</l>
               <l>Lamenting lowde my <hi>Daphnes</hi> Elegie,</l>
               <l>Helpe me to wayle my miſerable caſe,</l>
               <l>And when life parts, vouchſafe to cloſe mine eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye more happie Louers, which enioy</l>
               <l>The preſence of your deareſt loues delight,</l>
               <l>When ye doo heare my ſorrowfull annoy,</l>
               <l>Yet pittie me in your empaſsiond ſpright,</l>
               <l>And thinke that ſuch miſhap, as chaunſt to me,</l>
               <l>May happen vnto the moſt happieſt wight;</l>
               <l>For all mens ſtates alike vnſtedfaſt be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye my fellow Shepheards, which do feed</l>
               <l>Your careleſſe flocks on hils and open plaines,</l>
               <l>With better fortune, than did me ſucceed,</l>
               <l>Remember yet my vndeſerued paines,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:12"/>
               <l>And when ye heare, that I am dead or ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Lament my lot, and tell your fellow ſwaines,</l>
               <l>That ſad <hi>Alcyon</hi> dyde in lifes diſdaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye faire Damſels Shepheards dere delights,</l>
               <l>That with your loues do their rude hearts poſſeſſe,</l>
               <l>When as my hearſe ſhall happen to your ſightes,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe to deck the ſame with Cypareſſe;</l>
               <l>And euer ſprinckle brackiſh teares among,</l>
               <l>In pitie of my vndeſeru'd diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>The which I wretch, endured haue thus long.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And ye poore Pilgrimes, that with reſtleſſe toyle</l>
               <l>Wearie your ſelues in wandring deſert wayes,</l>
               <l>Till that you come, where ye your vowes aſſoyle,</l>
               <l>When paſsing by ye read theſe wofull layes</l>
               <l>On my graue written, rue my <hi>Daphnes</hi> wrong,</l>
               <l>And mourne for me that languiſh out my dayes:</l>
               <l>Ceaſe Shepheard, ceaſe, and end thy vnderſong.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus when he ended had his heauie plaint,</l>
               <l>The heauieſt plaint that euer I heard ſound,</l>
               <l>His checkes wext pale, and ſprights began to faint,</l>
               <l>As if againe he would haue fallen to ground;</l>
               <l>Which when I ſaw, I (ſtepping to him light)</l>
               <l>Amooued him out of his ſtonie ſwound,</l>
               <l>And gan him to recomfort as I might.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But he no waie recomforted would be,</l>
               <l>Nor ſuffer ſolace to approach him nie,</l>
               <l>But caſting vp aſdeinfull eie at me,</l>
               <l>That in his traunce I would not let him lie,</l>
               <l>Did rend his haire, and beat his blubbred face</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11630:13"/>
               <l>As one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>oſed wilfullie to die,</l>
               <l>That I ſore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>u'd to ſee his wretched caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Tho when the pang was ſomewhat ouerpaſt,</l>
               <l>And the outragious paſsion nigh appeaſed,</l>
               <l>I him deſirde, ſith daie was ouercaſt,</l>
               <l>And darke night faſt approched, to be pleaſed</l>
               <l>To turne aſide vnto my Cabinet,</l>
               <l>And ſtaie with me, till he were better eaſed</l>
               <l>Of that ſtrong ſtownd, which him ſo ſore beſet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But by no meanes I could him win thereto,</l>
               <l>Ne longer him intreate with me to ſtaie,</l>
               <l>But without taking leaue, he foorth did goe</l>
               <l>With ſtaggring pace and diſmall lookes diſmay,</l>
               <l>As if that death he in the face had ſeene,</l>
               <l>Or helliſh hags had met vpon the way:</l>
               <l>But what of him became I cannot weene.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
